# Cristovao Iglesias

 $Machine\ Learning \\ Researcher/Engineer$ 

 ♦ Spain/Switzerland
 ☑ cristovao.casagrande@gmail.com / cfrei096@uottawa.ca

**L** +34 677 48 27 82/+41 78 303 23 74 **𝚱** website **in** cristovao-iglesias **♀** cristovaoiglesias

## Summary

I am a Machine Learning (ML) researcher and engineer with a Ph.D. in Computer Science (focused on ML) and a strong background in software engineering. With over 10 years of experience in ML, my academic and professional journey has equipped me with a solid foundation for developing ML systems tailored to real-world applications.

### Skills

Languages: Pyhton, Java, Javascript, SQL (PostgreSQL, MySQL), R, Julia, Ruby on Rails, C++

General ML Libraries and Frameworks: Scikit-Learn, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch

Developer Tools: Git, Docker, AWS Stack, Elasticsearch, Grafana, Kibana

Data Processing and Analysis: Pandas, NLTK, NumPy, SciPy

Expertise: Deep learning, Bayesian modeling, federated learning, NLP, LLM, and data fusion.

### Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science (Machine Learning)	2020/09 - 2024/09
University of Ottawa, Canada	
M.Sc. in Informatics	2017/09 - 2019/10
Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil	
B.Sc. in Information Systems	2016/09 - 2019/11
Estácio de Sá University, Brazil	
B.Sc. in Biophysics (Bioinformatics)	2008/03 - 2013/03
Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil	

## Work Experience

### Machine Learning Research Assistant, Canada University of Ottawa

2021/01 - present

- Conducted advanced machine learning research, contributing to theoretical advancements and practical applications.
- Published research findings in journals and leading conferences (ICML, NeurIPS and FUSION).
- o Co-supervisor of two undergraduate students.

### Machine Learning Engineer, Canada University of Ottawa

2020/02 - 2020/12

• Designed and implemented novel machine learning algorithms and systems to address real-world challenges.

#### Web Development Professor, Brazil Mundial and Mare Bank

2019/05 - 2019/10

• Web Development using Javascript.

Software Engineer, Brazil Clavis Information Security (clavis.com.br)

2017/03 - 2019/04

- Designed and developed new functionalities for security products using AWS stack, Python, Ruby on Rails, SQL, Elasticsearch, and Grafana.
- Enhanced the efficiency of stress (load) testing by reducing latency in final report delivery by 85% with improvements in data processing and analysis capabilities.
- Proposed a new product component for malicious URL detection using LSTM.

## Software Engineer (Intern), Brazil EMC<sup>2</sup>

09/2014 - 03/2015

• Developed of plugins for Redmine using Ruby on Rails and PostgreSQL.

#### Software Engineer (Intern), Australia NICTA

12/2012 - 03/2013

• Developed a visualization and analysis tool for the web in the GWAS area to work with genomic data. Development using Python, JavaScript, Python, D3.js.

Software Engineer (Intern), Brazil Laboratório de Bioinformática e Biologia Computacional, INCA

2012/06 - 2012/11

• Modeled a relational database to analyze experimental protocols for obtaining protein three-dimensional structures. Development with MySQL and Python.

Bioinformatics Researcher (Intern), France Laboratoire de Biotechnologie et Pharmacologie Génétique Appliquée, ENSC

01/2011 - 02/2011

• Studied the initial steps of activation of BAX by BIM (BH3) through normal modes analysis of the vibration (NMA), optimization techniques, Python, cluster analysis, and analysis of modes consensus.

Bioinformatics Researcher (Intern), Brazil Laboratory for Molecular Dynamics and Modelling, UFRJ

03/2009 - 01/2011

- o Developed tools and molecular dynamics simulation for drug design.
- Project developed using C/C++, Python, R, optimizations techniques, PCA, cluster analysis, and data Mining techniques

## **Current Projects**

## Enhancing the performance of fine-tuning of LLM with surrogate Bayesian model.

- Responsible for designing and implementing the surrogate Bayesian model, ensemble of LLM, and fine-tuning evaluation.
- o Tools: Python, PyTorch, Llama, Mistral, Stable diffusion models, LoRa.
- Role: ML researcher
- o Sponsors: Universality of Ottawa and Federal University of Rio de Janeiro

## Completed Projects

# A platform for automatic designing of resilient IoT applications from requirements documents with LLM

code: RITA 🗹

- Responsible for the design and implementation of the platform architecture, dataset, and fine-tuning evaluation.
- Tools: Python, Docker, PyTorch, Fine-tuning LLM, NLP, MySQL, RoBERTa, GPT-3, NER, Anvil framework, Pandas, NumPy, and Seaborn, BERT, Transformers, ElMo.
- $\circ$  Publications: [5, 10, 13]
- Role: ML researcher/engineer

# New Bayesian filtering approaches for fast and low-cost bioprocess monitoring with uncertainty quantification

Doc: Thesis 🗹

- Responsible for designing, implementing, and evaluating three new Bayesian filtering approaches.
- Tools: Python, Julia, Docker, Bayesian filtering, Bayesian deep learning, hybrid models, uncertainty quantification, data fusion, Neural ODE, EKF, UKF, CKF, Global optimization, Genetic Algorithm, Bayesian Optimization.
- $\circ$  Publications: [8, 9, 11, 12, 12]
- o Role: ML researcher

# A Real-Time Respiration Monitoring and Classification System using a Doc: Journal Article 🗹 Depth Camera and Radars

- Main responsible for designing and implementing the real-time monitoring and classification tasks.
- o Tools: Random forest classifier, Python, C++, depth camera, data fusion and radar sensors.
- Publications: [2]
- Role: ML engineer

### Monitoring elderly people in nursing homes

• Main responsible for the implementation of the system.

o Tools: Python, cameras and movement sensors.

• Role: ML engineer

## Enabling uncertainty quantification in federated-learning clients

• Responsible for designing and implementing the two students (algorithm).

o Tools: Python, Julia, federated learning, deep learning, ensemble, Gaussian process regression

• Publications: [7]

• Role: ML researcher/engineer

## Enabling decision-making modeling for Personalized Monitoring System

• Responsible for the design and implementation of the probabilistic domain model.

 Tools: Python, Bayesian network, UML, data fusion, uncertainty quantification, conceptual model (software engineering)

code: 2S

code: DEMDE

 $\circ$  Publications: [4,6]

o Role: ML researcher/engineer

# Handling Massive Proportion of Missing Labels in Multivariate Long code: handlingMPML Term Time Series Forecasting

- Responsible for designing and implementing the two-step process approach where interpolation and model predictions are separated to enable the integration of prior domain knowledge.
- o Tools: Python, TensorFlow, Gaussian process regression, LSTM, Deep Learning
- Publications: [3]
- o Role: ML researcher/engineer

## Agile software development learning through open hardware project Doc: Conference Article

- Responsible for teaching Agile Methods through an Open Hardware project.
- o Tools: Arduino, Scrum, Extreme Programming (XP), Lean Kanban, Lean Startup Techniques

• Publications: [1],

• Role: Software engineer

#### **Publications**

- [1] Avelino F Gomes Filho, Carlos FC De Resende, Cristóvão F Iglesias, José G Mayworm, Marco EO Jardim, Raphael D Paiva, and Rodrigo De Toledo. Agile software development learning through open hardware project. In 2015 6th Brazilian Workshop on Agile Methods (WBMA), pages 40–47. IEEE, 2015.
- [2] Shan He, Zixiong Han, Cristóvão Iglesias, Varun Mehta, and Miodrag Bolic. A real-time respiration monitoring and classification system using a depth camera and radars. *Frontiers in Physiology*, 13:799621, 2022.
- [3] Cristovão Iglesias, Varun Mehta, Alina Venereo-Sanchez, Xingge Xu, Julien Robitaille, Robert Voyer, René Richard, Nabil Belacel, Amine Kamen, and Miodrag Bolic. Handling massive proportion of missing labels in multivariate long-term time series forecasting. In *Journal of Physics: Conference Series*, volume 2090, page 012170. IOP Publishing, 2021.
- [4] Cristóvão Iglesias, Claudio Miceli, and David Silva. A domain model for personalized monitoring system based on context-aware data fusion. In 2019 22th International Conference on Information Fusion (FUSION), pages 1–8. IEEE, 2019.
- [5] Cristovão F Iglesias, Rongchen Guo, Pedro Nucci, Claudio Miceli, and Miodrag Bolic. Automated extraction of iot critical objects from iot storylines, requirements and user stories via nlp. In 2023 10th IEEE Swiss Conference on Data Science (SDS), pages 104–107. IEEE, 2023.
- [6] Cristovão F Iglesias, Pedro Nucci, Claudio Miceli, and Miodrag Bolic. Demde: Decision making design based on bayesian network for personalized monitoring system. In 2023 26th International Conference on Information Fusion (FUSION), pages 1–8. IEEE, 2023.

- [7] Cristovão Iglesias Jr, Sidney Alves de Outeiro, Claudio Miceli de Farias, and Miodrag Bolic. Two students: Enabling uncertainty quantification in federated learning clients. In NeurIPS 2024 Workshop on Bayesian Decision-making and Uncertainty.
- [8] Cristovão Freitas Iglesias Jr and Miodrag Bolic. How not to make the joint extended kalman filter fail with unstructured mechanistic models. Sensors, 24(2), 2024.
- [9] Cristovão Freitas Iglesias Jr and Miodrag Bolic. Limitations of joint and dual nonlinear kalman estimators in low-cost bioprocess monitoring. workshop LXAI of ICML 2024, 24(2), 2024.
- [10] Cristovao Freitas Iglesias Jr, Claudio Miceli, and Miodrag Bolic. An architectural design decision model for resilient iot application. arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.10429, 2023.
- [11] Cristovão Freitas Iglesias Jr, Milica Ristovski, Miodrag Bolic, and Miroslava Cuperlovic-Culf. raav manufacturing: the challenges of soft sensing during upstream processing. *Bioengineering*, 10(2):229, 2023.
- [12] Cristovão Freitas Iglesias Jr, Xingge Xu, Varun Mehta, Mounia Akassou, Alina Venereo-Sanchez, Nabil Belacel, Amine Kamen, and Miodrag Bolic. Monitoring the recombinant adeno-associated virus production using extended kalman filter. *Processes*, 10(11):2180, 2022.
- [13] Luis Eduardo Pessoa, Cristovao Freitas Iglesias Jr, and Claudio Miceli. Rita: Automatic framework for designing of resilient iot applications. *LaFUSION*, 2024.